Louis-Alexandre Berthier Collection, 1780-1783: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Special Collections.
- Series 2: March of the French Army from Providence to Virginia, March 1781 - October 1781, 10 portfolios (1 partial)
  - Road Maps of the French Army's March from the Hudson to Virginia, August - September, 1781, dates not examined; more than 18 packets 23 x 16 cm (dimensions of cahier when closed; the fold-out sheets are of varying width) (Portfolio VIII, Packet 15)
    - 120. Gué de Falmouth ... Chem de Frédérickbourg, Santier for manvais mais abrégeant de plus de moitié sur le grand chemin, undated; 1 item 17 x 27.5 cm (Portfolio VIII, Packet 19)
      Ford at Falmouth across the Rappahannock River. July 1782. According to Clermont-Crèvecœur (p. 73), the artillery used this ford, which was particularly bad. The infantry and the wagons, however, were ferried across; cf. Verger's journal, p. 159, and Von Closen, p. 210. The road at lower left, an alternate route from Fredericksburg to the ferry, is described here as "a very bad path, but shortening the distance over the main road by more than half."
      MS, No. 19. [Rice/Brown, p. 177]
  - 26. Plans des differents camps occupés par L'Armée aux orfres de M. Le Comte de Rochambeau, undated; more than 35 packets 32 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21)
    Plans of the Different Camps occupied by the Army under the Orders of the Comte de Rochambeau: Campaign of 1781. This is the cover of a "cahier" containing maps of the army's camps from Rhode Island to Virginia. The key indicates that artillery units are tinted in pink, French troops yellow, and American troops green. Light-green tinted areas marked "b" show "bois," i.e., woods; blue designates water. Note also that the yellow-tinted symbols for French regiments, when enclosed in a dotted line, indicate positions occupied in 1782 (on the northward return march from Virginia to New England) by the Royal Deux-Ponts and Saintonge regiments, then marching together as a brigade. Since some of these maps thus combine information concerning the 1781 and 1782 campaigns, it is evident that the finished copies were not completed until after 1782, perhaps after Berthier's return to France.
    MS, No. 21. The dimensions noted for the camp plans are the outside measurements of the sheet on which the original was drawn. [Rice/Brown, pp. 131-132]
    For a single surviving example of the rough field sketches made on the spot, see No. 150. These maps of the 1781 camps are from the Berthier Collection, Princeton University Library, formerly in the Château de Grosbois. A second set, now in the Library of Paul Mellon, was once among Rochambeau's papers in the Chateau de Rochambeau. A few minor variations, such as the omission of certain names, seem to signify that the General's set was copied from Berthier's own set. Still another series of these camp plans, somewhat similar to the Berthier set but much smaller in size, are included in a manuscript entitled "Précis des Opérations et des Marches de l'Armée combinée française et américaine pendant la Campagne de 1781" in the Henry E. Huntington Library, San Marino, California (MS HM 621); see "Checklist of Journals," s.v. Soisonnais Regiment.
    For further commentary on the localities represented, see Itineraries 1 and 2, and the pertinent parts of the journals of Clermont-Crèvecœur and of Berthier.
    - 27. Camp à Providence le 10 et 11 Juin, 30 miles de Newport; cette Marche s'est faite par eau, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-1)
      First Camp at Providence. 10-11 June 1781. As stated in the heading, the troops had come from Newport to Providence by water. The road junction above the letter "P" in the word Providence represents the corner of present Westminster and Weybosset Streets. The "chemin de Waterman's Tavern" (leading to the next campsite) is present Cranston Street.
      The army camped again on this site in November 1782, where the units shown within dotted lines are positioned on the present map; see note to No. 156.
      MS, No. 21-1. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 132]
    - 28. Camp à Waterman's Tavern le 18 Juin, quinze miles de Providence, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-2)
      Second Camp at Waterman's Tavern. 18-21 June 1781. Fifteen miles from the preceding camp at Providence. The dates on the maps of the camps, here and subsequently, are those of the arrival of the First Division. Since the army was marching in four divisions, each camp was occupied on at least four successive days. The maps are so oriented that the direction of the march is at the top of the sheet. The incoming and outgoing roads are generally designated by the point of departure of the day's march and by the next day's destination: in this instance, the Providence road and the Plainfield road. Waterman's Tavern is in the town of Coventry, Rhode Island. The "chemin de Providence" is now Matteson Road. The tavern itself is on Maple Valley Road. The "meeting-house" is no longer standing; State of Rhode Island Historic Cemetery, Coventry 37, is near the site. The stream on the left is Turkey Meadow Brook.
      The army camped again on this site, by brigades, in November 1782, as indicated here by the units enclosed in dotted lines.
      MS, No. 21-2. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 132]
    - 29. Camp à Plainfield, le 19 Juin, 15 miles de Waterman's Tavern, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-3)
      Third Camp at Plainfield [in Connecticut]. 19-22 June 1781. Fifteen miles from the preceding camp at Waterman's Tavern. Plainfield's main street, running from south to north (left to right on the map), is present State Route 12. The stream, to the west of which the camp was located, is Horse Brook.
      MS, No. 21-3. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 133]
    - 30. Camp à Windham, le 20 Juin, 15 miles de Plainfield, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-4)
      Fourth Camp at Windham. 20-23 June 1781. Fifteen miles from the preceding camp at Plainfield. The pattern of the town, as shown here, is readily recognizable today. The "Windham River," on the east bank of which the army camped, is now called the Shetucket. "Chemin de Marshfield" is presumably an error for Mansfield.
      On its return march in November 1782 the army camped again at Windham, but on a different site, east of the town; see No. 153.
      MS, No. 21-4. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 133]
    - 31. Camp à Bolton, le 21 Juin, 16 miles de Windham, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-5)
      Fifth Camp at Bolton. 21-24 June 1781. Sixteen miles from the preceding camp at Windham. Bolton, with its "meeting house," is now known as Bolton Center, along the Hop River valley and over Bolton Notch.
      The army marched through Bolton Center again in November 1782 but camped "2 miles beyond Bolton Meetinghouse," as shown on map, No. 152.
      MS, No. 21-5. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 133]
    - 32. Camp à East-hartford, le 22 Juin, 12 1/2 miles de Bolton, le 23 and 24 Séjour, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-6)
      Sixth Camp at East Hartford. 22-28 June 1781. Twelve and a half miles from the preceding camp at Bolton Center. Each of the four infantry regiments halted here for two extra days. The positions shown nearest to the Connecticut River indicate the camp of the Bourbonnais on the right (22-23-24 June, replaced by the Saintonge, 25-26-27 June) and the Royal Deux-Ponts on the left (23-24-25 June). The position along the road from Bolton, in the lower part of the map, is that of the Soissonnais (24-25-26 June). Since the Saintonge departed only on 28 June, the East Hartford camp was occupied continuously from the 22nd to the 28th. The stream at the lower part of the map is the Hockanum River.
      The 1782 encampment at East Hartford is shown on map, No. 151.
      MS, No. 21-6. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 133]
    - 33. Camp à Farmington, le 25 Juin, 12 1/2 miles de East-hartford, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-7)
      Seventh Camp at Farmington. 25-28 June 1781. Twelve and a half miles from the preceding camp at East Hartford. This map shows only the southern part of Farmington's Main Street (cf. map of the 1782 camp, No. 149, which includes the northern part of the street). The brook at the bottom of the map, flowing under the road and into the larger stream at the right (Pequabuck), is Diamond Glen Brook. The camp ("a mile from Farmington," according to Itinerary 2, above) was on the west side of the main road (present Route 10) just beyond its junction with Scott Swamp Road (present Route 6).
      MS, No. 21-7. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, pp. 133-134]
    - 34. Camp à Barn's Tavern, le 26 Juin, 13 miles de Farmington, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-8)
      Eighth Camp at Barnes's Tavern. 26-29 1781. Thirteen miles from the preceding camp at Farmington. The tavern kept by Asa Barnes was in the locality now known as Marion in the southwestern part of the town of Southington. A local historian, the Reverend Herman R. Timlow, in his Sketches of Southington, Conn. (Hartford, 1875) notes that in June 1781 "the French army, under the command of Count de Rochambeau passed through the town," and adds: "Marshall[!] Berthier was aid to the Count."
      The position shown within dotted lines denotes the second of two regiments that camped here together on 26-27 October 1782, when the army was marching by brigades.
      MS, No. 21-8. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 134]
    - 35. Camp à Break-Neck, le 27 Juin, 13 miles de Barn's Tavern, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-9)
      Ninth Camp at Break Neck. 27-30 June 1781. Thirteen miles from the preceding camp at Barnes's Tavern. Break Neck Hill is in the town of Middlebury. The stream is Hop Brook; its enlargement is now called Abbott's Pond. Bronson's Tavern (here shown left of letter "B") is on present Artillery Road. The portion of the road passing through the encampment (artillery on left side) is now abandoned; only the right-hand swing of the loop remains. As denoted by the regimental symbol enclosed in a dotted line, the French camped here again in October 1782 when marching in the opposite direction on their way to Hartford and Providence.
      MS, No. 21-9. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 134]
    - 36. Camp à New-Town, le 28 Juin, 15 miles de Break-Neck, le 29 and 30 Séjour, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-10)
      Tenth Camp at Newtown. 28 June - 2 July 1781. Fifteen miles from the preceding camp at Break Neck. The four divisions are shown, with a detachment of grenadiers and chasseurs in a forward position west of Newtown's Main Street (which runs roughly north and south). The army camped again at Newtown on 24-26 October 1782.
      MS, No. 21-10. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown. p. 134]
    - 37. Camp à Ridgebury, le ler Juillet, 15 miles de New-Town, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-11)
      Eleventh Camp at Ridgebury [in Connecticut]. 1-3 July 1781. Fifteen miles from the preceding camp at Newtown. Ridgebury, not far from the New York State line, is a hamlet in the morthern part of the town of Ridgefield. The present Congregational Church (built in 1851) is on the site of the "meeting-house" shown on the map.
      The army marched over this route again in October 1782 but did not then stop to camp at Ridgebury.
      MS, No. 21-11. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 134]
    - 38. Camp à Bedford, le 2 Juillet, 14 miles de Ridgebury, manque, n'ayant pas été figuré; et Camp à North-Castle, le 3 Juillet, 5 miles de Bedford, le 4 Séjour, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-12/13)
      Thirteenth Camp at North Castle [Mount Kisco, New York]. 3-6 July 1781. The First Brigade, which left the Ridgebury camp on 2 July and bivouaked that night at Bedford, and the Second Brigade, which marched the whole distance from Ridgebury on 3 July, both reached North Castle on 3 July. As mentioned in the heading of the map, no plan of the Bedford (Village) bivouac of the First Brigade was drawn. North Castle is present Mount Kisco, Westchester County, New York. The "Etang" or pond, formerly known as Kirby Pond, no longer exists; the area is part of present Leonard Recreation Park. The stream flowing out of the pond is the Kisco River. The North Castle "meeting house," shown here, was St. George's Church (built in 1761); it no longer stands, but an old cemetery still marks the site.
      A French hospital was maintained at North Castle during the period of the long encampment farther south at Philipsburg. There was a bivouac here at North Castle, 20 August 1781, when the army was proceeding north from Philipsburg to King's Ferry; see notes to Nos. 48 and 61.
      MS, No. 21-12/13. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, pp. 134-135]
      See also Richard G. Lucid and Arthur I. Bernhard, "Northcastle Camp," The Westchester Historian (Westchester County Historical Society), XXXV, No. 1 (Jan.-March 1959), 3-8.
      Regarding the French hopsital, see Blanchard's journal (I), p. 82; Dawson, Français Morts aux Etats Unis, pp. 30, 56, 71.
    - 39. Camp à Phillipsburg, le 15 Juillet, 17 1/2 miles de North-Castle, Séjour jusqu'au 19 Aoust, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-14)
      Fourteenth Camp at Philipsburg [New York]. Seventeen and a half miles from the preceding camp at North Castle. Rochambeau's army camped here with Washington's army from 5 July 1781 until 19 August. Both French and American campsites are shown: French in yellow, American dark green. South is at the top of the map. The Bronx River is at the left, the Sawmill River is at the right. The Dobbs Ferry road, upper right, leads to the banks of the Hudson.
      MS, No. 21-14. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 135]
    - 61. Bivoüac à North-Castle, le 19 Aoust, 17 1/2 miles d Phillip'sburg, le 20 Séjour et Camp à Huntz-Tavern, le 21 Aoust, 8 miles de North-Castle, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-15/16)
      Sixteenth Camp at Hunt's Tavern. 21 August 1781. This was the second camp after Philipsburg. There is no map of the previous day's bivouac at North Castle (Mount Kisco). Hunt's Tavern was situated in present Yorktown, Westchester County, New York, on what is now designated as State Route 35 (U.S. 202) near the corner of Hallock's Mill Road, opposite Baldwin Road. The two ponds (étangs) shown on the map are Mohansic Lake and Crom Pond. The roads at the left of the sheet lead westward to New Bridge at the mouth of the Croton River. The four divisions with field artillery units are shown, as well as detachments of grenadiers and chasseurs, and Lauzun's Legion, the latter serving here as a rear guard facing the enemy to the southward.
      The French army camped here again in the autumn of 1782 when returning from Virginia to New England. See Nos. 145 and 146, the map of its so-called Crompond encampment, where it remained from 17 September to 20 October 1782.
      MS, No. 21-15/16. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, pp. 146-147]
    - 62. Camp à King's ferry, où Verplank, le 22 Aoust, 14 miles de Huntz-Tavern. Le 23 Séjour, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-17)
      Seventeenth Camp at King's Ferry or Verplanck. 22-24 August 1781. Fourteen miles from the preceding camp at Hunt's Tavern. The crossing of the Hudson at King's Ferry is described in Clermont-Crèvecœur's journal (p. 40) and in Berthier's journal (p. 255). Berthier, who supervised the crossing of the wagons, notes that the last vehicle had crossed the river by midnight on 25 August. The road to New Bridge, at the left of the map, is the route by which the Americans reached King's Ferry. The fort shown here is above the letters "nk" of "Verplank" is Fort LaFayette, of the east bank of the Hudson.
      MS, No. 21-17. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 147].
    - 63. Camp à Haver-Straw, le 24 Aoust, 2 miles du Ferry, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-18)
      Eighteenth Camp at Haverstraw. 24-25 August 1781. Two miles from King's Ferry. The army was now marching by brigades of two divisions each. The date on the map is that of the arrival of the First Brigade. The "Haverstraw" camp, the first after the crossing of the Hudson (and the eighteenth since the departure from Providence, Rhode Island) was in the locality now known as Stony Point Village (as distinguished from the Point proper). The designation "Haverstraw" is correct, since the name applied in 1781 to a larger area than the present town of Haverstraw, which is farther south. The larger of the two streams shown here is Cedar Pond Brook, flowing eastward into the Hudson.
      In September 1782 one brigade camped again on this site; see No. 142.
      MS, No. 21-18. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 147].
    - 64. Camp à Suffrantz (Suffern), le 25 Aoust, 15 1/2 miles de Haver-Straw, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-19)
      Nineteenth Camp at Suffern [in New York]. 25-26 August 1781. Fifteen and a half miles from the preceding camp at Haverstraw (Stony Point Village). The stream at the left of the map is the Ramapo River, here flowing roughly south.
      The army camped here again in 1782, as shown on map No. 141.
      MS, No. 21-19. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 147]
    - 65. Camp à Pompton-Meeting-house, le 26 Aoust, 15 miles de Suffrantz, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-20)
      Twentieth Camp at Pompton Meetinghouse [in New Jersey]. 26-27 August 1781. Fifteen miles from the preceding camp at Suffern. The "meeting-house" shown on the map is the Dutch Reformed Church; the present church building and adjacent cemetery are on the same site, along the Newark-Pompton Turnpike, the main street of Pompton Plains, Morris County, New Jersey.
      The army camped again at Pompton Plains on its return march in September 1782, as shown on map, No. 140.
      MS, No. 21-20. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 148]
    - 66. Camp à Wippany le 27 Aoust, 15 miles Pompton-Meeting-house. Le 28 Séjour, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-21)
      Twenty-First Camp at Whippany. 27-29 August 1781. Fifteen miles from the preceding camp at Pompton Plains. The First Brigade halted here a second day, so that the entire army was in camp here on the 28th. Both brigades are shown. The map also indicates, by means of dotted lines, positions occupied when the army camped here again, northward bound, on 10-11 September 1782. The camp was located on grounds now occupied by the Bell Telephone Laboratories, the Seeing Eye, and some adjacent houses on the high ground between Whippany Road (the main east-west road on the map, i.e., the road from Whippany to Morristown) and the northwest edge of the Black (or Columbia) Meadows. The top of the map is approximately south. Roads leading off the left edge of the map went eastward to Chatham, the sightly position where Rochambeau had decoy bake ovens built to make the British believe an attack on New York was imminent. Washington, who led the American army through New Jersey by a route paralleling the French to the east, had his headquarters temporarily at Chatham. The road leading off the right of the map went to Morristown (and eventually to Bullion's Tavern, the destination of the next march). "Hanover" was, and is, the name of the township of which Whippany is a part.
      MS, No. 21-21. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 148]
    - 67. Camp à Bullion's Tavern, le 29 Aoust, 16 miles de Wippany, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-22)
      Twenty-Second Camp at Bullion's Tavern [Liberty Corner]. 29-30 August 1781. Sixteen miles from the preceding camp at Whippany. Bullion's Tavern was at the locality later called Liberty Corner, in Pernards Township, Somerset County, New Jersey. The spelling "Bullion" (probably a corruption of Boylan) also appears on American maps of the period. The stream shown on the map is Harrison's Brook, a tributary of Dead River, which in turn joins the Passaic. The sharp right-angle turn in the road still provides an unmistakable point of referende for identification of the site of the French camp. The road at top of map, left, was the route leading eventually to Quibbletown (New Market), Scotch Plains, or Chatham.
      The army's 1782 encampment at Bullion's Tavern is shown on map, No. 139.
      MS, No. 21-22. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 148]
    - 68. Camp à Sommerset Court-house, le 30 Aoust, 13 miles de Bullion's Tavern, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-23)
      Twenty-third Camp at Somerset Courthouse [Millstone]. 30-31 August 1781. Thirteen miles from the preceding camp at Bullion's Tavern. Somerset Courthouse is now called Millstone. The stream, which flows north into the Raritan, is the Millstone River. The courthouse, near the second of the three bridges shown here, had been burned in October 1779 by British raiders under Lieutenant Colonel Simcoe. The road through the village taken by the army is essentially present State Route 533, which has been straightened to eliminate the bow leading down to the bridge. The two infantry regiments and artillery camped near the Dutch Reformed Church (present edifice [1827] and adjacent cemetery on same site) at the junction of present State Routes 533 and 514. Beyond the encampment, at a bend in the road, is the Van Doren house, still standing on this site.
      The separate unit, on right of the map, represents Lauzun's Legion. Rumors of a British sortie from New York reached the army here at Somerset Courthouse. Fearing an attack, the Baron de Viomenil (who was then in command, Rochambeau having ridden ahead) ordered patrols to the eastward. Lauzun ([2], p. 293) relates that he himself with 50 of his husars rode 10 miles out along the New Brunswick road: "I met two or three sizeable patrols of light troops, who retired after exchanging a few shots with my hussars. I satisfied myself that the English army was not on the march, and then returned to reassure the Baron."
      The army camped again at Millstone on its return march in 1782; see No. 138.
      MS, No. 21-23. Rochambeau's copy is in the Library of Paul Mellon, Upperville, Virginia. [Rice/Brown, p. 149]
      Photographs of the Van Doren house and of the site of the courthouse are in Elizabeth G.C. Menzies, Millstone Valley (New Brunswick, 1969), pp. 146, 236, 244, 262.
    - 69. Camp à Prince-town, le 31 Aoust, 14 miles de Sommerset Court-house, undated; 1 item 33 x 21 cm (Portfolio IX, Packet 21-24)